Zeynep Ersoy

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER IN UNIVERSIDADE DE ÉVORA | RUI NABEIRO BIODIVERSITY CHAIR

Summary _

I'm an early-career aquatic ecologist with extensive international experience (Turkey, Denmark, Spain, Germany, Portugal). My research centers on understanding the response of aquatic food webs to global climate crisis and other environmental perturbations, using approaches ranging from mesocosm experiments to biodiversity monitoring to investigate trophic interactions, energy transfer, ecosystem functioning and health.

Research Experience _____



The Rui Nabeiro Biodiversity Chair, Universidade de Évora

Évora, Portugal

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Jul.2019 - Mar.2022

- Project: AdaptAlentejo: Predicting ecosystem-level responses to climate change
- Advisors: Miguel Matias & Miguel Araujo

University of Vic-Central University of Catalonia (UVic-UCC)

Vic, Spain

Jul.2015 - Dec. 2018

- Doctoral thesis work in Aquatic Ecology Research Group



Leibniz-Institute of Freshwater Biology and Inland Fisheries (IGB)

Berlin, Germany

GUEST PHD FELLOW

Apr. - Dec. 2016

- Project: Recovery rate of zooplankton body size distributions after massive fish predation
- Advisor: Thomas Mehner

Aarhus University, Lake Ecology Group

Aarhus, Denmark

VISITING RESEARCH STUDENT

Feb. - Jun. 2014

- Project: Assessment of changes in macrophyte communities in Lake Stigsholm using long-term monitoring data
- Advisors: Martin Søndergaard & Torben Lauridsen



Middle East Technical University, Department of Biological Sciences

Ankara, Turkey

RESEARCH AND TEACHING ASSISTANT

Jan.2013 - Jun. 2015

- 4 semesters of teaching in practical undergraduate courses



REFRESH EU Project - REFRESH

Ankara, Turkey

PROJECT ASSISTANT

2012 - 2014

- Project: Adaptive strategies to mitigate the impacts of climate change on European freshwater ecosystems

Education _

University of Vic-Central University of Catalonia (UVic-UCC)

Vic, Spain

PHD IN EXPERIMENTAL SCIENCES AND TECHNOLOGY PROGRAM

2015 - 2018

- Thesis: Biotic and environmental factors shaping body size distributions in freshwater planktonic food webs
- Advisors: Sandra Brucet & Mireia Bartrons

Middle East Technical University (METU)

Ankara, Turkey

MSc in Biology, specialized in Limnology

2012 - 2015

- **Thesis:** Impact of nutrient and water level changes on the submerged macrophytes along a latitudinal gradient: A Pan-European mesocosm experiment
- Advisor: Meryem Beklioğlu
- CGPA: 3.93/4.00

METU Middle East Technical University (METU)

Ankara, Turkey 2007 - 2012

BSC IN BIOLOGY (MAJOR) AND ENVIRONMENTAL MICROBIOLOGY (MINOR)

- CGPA: 3.66/4.00 (Ranked 3rd among 50 Biology graduates)

Publications & Presentations

PUBLISHED JOURNAL ARTICLES

- Hintz, W. D., Arnott, S. E., Symons, C. C., Greco, D. A., McClymont, A., Brentrup, J. A., Cañedo-Argüelles, M., Derry, A. M., Downing, A. L., Gray, D. K., Melles, S. J., Relyea, R. A., Rusak, J., Searle, C. L., Astorg, L., Baker, H. K., Beisner, B. E., Cottingham, K. L., Ersoy, Z. et al., Current water quality guidelines across North America and Europe do not protect lakes from salinization. PNAS (2022), doi:10.1073/pnas.2115033119
- Hébert, M. P., Symons, C. C., Cañedo-Argüelles, M., Arnott, S. E., Derry, A. M., Fugère, V., Hintz, W. D., Melles, S. J., Astorg, L., Baker, H. K., Brentrup, J. A., Downing, A. L., Ersoy, Z. et al., Lake salinization drives consistent losses of zooplankton abundance and diversity across coordinated mesocosm experiments. Limnology & Oceanography Letters (2022), doi:10.1002/lol2.10239
- Ersoy, Z.[‡], Scharfenberger, U.[‡], Baho, D.L., Bucak, T., Feldmann, T., Hejzlar, J., Levi, E.E., Mahdy, A., Nõges, T., Papastergiadou, E., Stefanidis, K., Šorf, M., Søndergaard, M., Trigal, C., Jeppesen, E., Beklioğlu, M. Impact of nutrients and water level changes on submerged macrophytes along a temperature gradient: a Pan-European mesocosm experiment. Global Change Biology (2020), 26, 6831-6851, doi:10.1111/gcb.15338
- Ersoy, Z., Brucet, S., Bartrons, M., Mehner, T. Experimental tests of fish predation on zooplankton, and recovery rate of zooplankton community structure after stop of predation, PLoS ONE (2019), 14(2): e0212351, doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0212351
- Ersoy, Z., Jeppesen, E., Sgarzi, S., Arranz, I., Cañedo-Argüelles, M., Quintana, X.D., Landkildehus, F., Lauridsen, T.L., Bartrons, M., Brucet, S. Size-based interactions and trophic transfer efficiency are modified by fish predation and cyanobacteria blooms in Lake Mývatn, Iceland. Freshwater Biology (2017), 62, 1942-1952, doi:10.1111/fwb.13039
- Brucet, S., Tavşanoğlu, U.N., Ozen, A., Levi, E., Bezirci, G., Çakıroğlu, A.İ., Jeppesen, E., Svenning, J.C., Ersoy, Z., Beklioğlu, M. Size-based interactions across trophic levels of food webs in shallow Mediterranean lakes, Freshwater Biology (2017), 62, 1819-1830, doi:10.1111/fwb.12997
- 1. Cañedo-Argüelles, M., Sgarzi, S., Arranz, I., Quintana, X.D., **Ersoy, Z.**, Landkildehus, F., Lauridsen, T., Jeppesen, E., Brucet, S. Role of predation in biological communities in naturally eutrophic subarctic Lake Mývatn, Iceland, **Hydrobiologia (2017)**, 790,1,213223, **doi:10.1007/s10750-016-3031-0**

BOOK CHAPTERS

1. **Ersoy, Z.**, Elverici, M. Biodiversity indices in aquatic ecosystems Field and Laboratory Techniques in Freshwater Ecosystems, pp.393-410 (in Turkish) Editors: Nihan Tavşanoğlu, Gökben Kankılıç Başaran, Şeyda Erdoğan, Nobel Publishing, ISBN 978-625-402-870-0

ARTICLES IN REVIEW

- 2. **Ersoy, Z.**, Cañedo-Argüelles, M., Espinosa-Angona, C., Vendrell-Puigmitja, L., Proia, L. Experimental assessment of salinization effects on freshwater zooplankton communities and their trophic interactions under eutrophic conditions. Under review **Environmental Pollution**
- Arnott, S.E., Fugère, V., Symons, C.C., Melles S.J., Beisner, B.E., Cañedo-Argüelles, M., Hébert, M. P., Brentrup, J.A., Downing, A. L, Gray, D.K., Greco, D., William D. Hintz, W.D., McClymont, A., Rick A. Relyea, R.A., James A. Rusak, J.A., Searle, C.L., Astorg, L., Baker, H.K., Ersoy, Z. et al., Broad scale intraspecific variation in freshwater zooplankton salt tolerance. In Revision in Limnology & Oceanography Letters

ARTICLES SUBMITTED AND IN PREPARATION

- 3. **Ersoy, Z.**, Castillo-Escrivà, A., Pereira, CL., Sroczynska, K., Ribeiro, S., Araújo, MB., Matias, MG. Environment mediates body mass-abundance scaling regardless of species richness. Submitted to **Ecology**
- 2. Pereira, CL.[‡], **Ersoy, Z.**[‡] Gravel, D., Araújo, MB., Matias, MG. Future-proofing environmental DNA and trait-based predictions of food webs. In prep for **TREE**
- 1. Sgarzi, S., Badosa, A., Leiva-Presa, À., Bartrons, M., **Ersoy, Z.**, López, E., Brucet, S. Water depth and resource availability mediate planktonic size spectra in temporary Mediterranean ponds along the hydroperiod. In prep. for **Aquatic Sciences**

[‡]Co-first authorship

ORAL PRESENTATIONS (INCLUDING ONLY FIRST AUTHOR TALKS IN THE LAST 5 YEARS)

- 11. **Ersoy, Z.** Ponds are full of different forms of life, let's take a closer look! **Lisbon Soapbox Science Event**, 23 October 2021, **Virtual**
- 10. **Ersoy, Z.**, Baker, H.K., McClymont, A., Hassal, E., Jonasen, K.L., Kirkwood, A., Melles, S., Searle, C.L, Shurin, J.B., Siddons, S.R., Symons, C.C., Cañedo- Argüelles, M. Effect of salinization on zooplankton size structure: an intercontinental coordinated mesocosm experiment, **SEFS 2021**, 25-30 July 2021, Virtual
- 9. **Ersoy, Z.**, Castillo-Escrivà A., Pereira CL., Sroczynska K., Ribeiro S., Araújo MB., Matias MG., Changes in community size structure in experimental freshwater food webs across biogeographical gradients, **ASLO 2021**, 22-27 June 2021, Virtual
- 8. Ersoy, Z., Pereira CL., Gilbert TP., Araújo MB., Matias MG., Reconstructing food webs in a multi-site meso-cosm facility- Iberian Pond Network, 2nd International Aquatic Mesocosm Research Symposium, 12-14 April 2021, Virtual
- Ersoy, Z., Castillo-Escrivà A., Pereira CL., Sroczynska K., Ribeiro S., Araújo MB., Matias MG., Abundance-body mass relationships structuring aquatic food webs across biogeographical gradients, AlL 2020, 26-29 October 2020, Virtual
- 6. Ersoy, Z. Size-abundance scaling across biogeographical gradients in aquatic food webs, International Biogeography Society, Humboldt Day Event, 12-19 September 2020, Virtual (invited talk)
- 5. **Ersoy, Z.** Tatlısu ekosistemlerinde besin ağları ve boyuta bağlı etkileşimler (in Turkish), **Eko-EvoOnline Seminars**, 10 July 2020, **Virtual (invited talk)**
- 4. **Ersoy, Z.**, Bartrons, M., Mehner, Jeppesen, E., Brucet, S. Influence of fish predation on size-based interactions and recovery of zooplankton communities in freshwater planktonic food webs: Examples from mesocosm experiments, **EEBST 2019**, 10-12 July 2019, Ankara, Turkey
- 3. **Ersoy, Z.**, García-Comas, C., Bartrons, M., Hsieh, C.H., Brucet, S. Influence of prey and predator size diversity on trophic transfer efficiency in freshwater and marine ecosystems, **SIBECOL 2019**, 4-7 February 2019, Barcelona, Spain
- 2. **Ersoy, Z.**, Bartrons, M., Mehner, T., Brucet, S. Recovery rate of zooplankton community structure after stop of fish predation, **AlL 2018**, 24-29 June 2018, Coimbra, Portugal
- 1. **Ersoy, Z.**, Jeppesen, E., Sgarzi, S., Quintana, X.D., Arranz, I., Cañedo, M., Landkildehus, F., Lauridsen T.L., Einarsson, Á., Brucet, S. Size-based interactions within the food web of Lake Mývatn, Iceland: a mesocosm experiment, **SIL 2016**, 31 July-5 August 2016, Torino, Italy

Projects

2022-Now	Co-PI- ACROSS-LAtitudinal gradients of speCies Richness and bOdy-Size Spectrum in multiple trophic levels and ecosystems, SIBECOL project Link	Worldwide
2022-Now	4th co-champion- GLEON ZooSize project Link	Worldwide
2019-Now	Researcher- AdaptAlentejo Predicting ecosystem-level responses to climate change	Portugal
2019-Now	Collaborator- GLEON - GALACTIC: GlobAl LAke miCroplasTICs Link	Portugal
2018-Now	Collaborator- GLEON - Global Salt Experiment Link	Spain
2018–2019	Collaborator- Urban Algae - Ecological Status and the Perception of Ecosystem Services of Urban Ponds (2 nd Collaborative European Freshwater Science Project for Young Researchers - FreshProject)	Spain
2016–2018	Collaborator- AGRHYDROM- A timely look at effects of agriculture on fluvial DOM: the role of hydrology, 2 nd Young Collaborative Project from the Iberian Association of Limnology (AIL)	Spain
2015–2017	Researcher- Restoration of Mediterranean temporary ponds in Can Torres (Serra de l'Albera). Funded by ANDRENA.	Spain
2014–2015	Researcher- Will climate—related changes in fish stocks lead to significant ecosystem shifts in the natural eutrophic Lake Myvatn (Iceland)? Funded by Carlsberg Foundation	Spain

Grants & Awards __

2022	SIBECOL Projects for Early Career Researchers (4k€)	Iberian Peninsula
2021	ASLO 2021 Aquatic Sciences Meeting Registration Grant (\$250)	Virtual, Worldwide
2018	Representative of Spain, SIL Student Competition for the best published article in Limnology	Vic, Spain
2018	AIL 2018 Conference Registration Grant (160€)	Coimbra, Portugal
2016	UVic-UCC, International Research Stay Grant (2k€)	Vic, Spain
2016	Wetzel SIL Congress Travel Award (\$225)	Turin, Italy
2016	International IGB Fellowship (8k€)	Berlin, Germany
2015	Antiga Caixa Manlleu & BBVA Foundation, International Mobility Grant (700€)	Vic, Spain
2015	UVic Predoctoral Fellowship (48k€)	Vic, Spain
2014	ERASMUS Student Mobility Grant (800€)	Aarhus, Denmark

Skills

- **Programming:** R (tidyverse, dplyr, nlme, mgcv, randomForest, igraph, Rmarkdown), Python (beginner)
- Languages: Turkish (native), English (proficient), Catalan (elementary), Spanish (beginner)
- **Fieldwork and Laboratory:** Invertebrate, plankton and water chemistry sampling, water chemistry analysis, plankton and invertebrate identification & enumeration, respirometry experiment

Memberships _____

2017-Present	European Fresh and Young Researchers (EFYR) representative of European Federation for Freshwater Scientists (EFFS)
2015-Present	Member, International Society of Limnology (SIL)
2015-Present	Member, Iberian Association of Limnology (AIL)
2015-Present	Member, Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Society of Turkey (Eko-Evo)

Academic Service & Outreach __

- **Supervision:** David José Batista Reisinho, Reconstructing the aquatic food web of the Alqueva dam: a bibliographic approach, 2019-2021, Master thesis at Universidade de Évora, co-supervised with Miguel Matias
- **Mentoring:** Álvaro Gómez Ramírez, Effect of global warming on the physiology of aquatic invertebrates, 2021, Bachelor thesis at Universidad de Alcalá, Spain
- Reviewer Journals: Hydrobiologia (2), Freshwater Biology (1), Aquatic Sciences (1), Water (1), PloS ONE (1), Climatic Change (1), Environmental Science and Pollution Research (1), Fundamental and Applied Limnology (1), Anais da Academia Brasileira de Ciências (1)
- **Reviewer Funding:** European Federation for Freshwater Scientists (EFFS) Collaborative European Freshwater Science Project- FreshProject
- **Science Communication:** Lisbon Soapbox Science Event Speaker (October 2021) and STEM mentoring at Epistem Turkey (2018-2020)
- Organizations: Organizing committee member 2nd Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Symposium, 8th Shallow Lakes Conference and SEFS 2019 and 2021